Guide to the Jacob Eliot Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jacob Eliot family papers
1716-1945
MS 193
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(3 boxes)
Diaries of Jacob Eliot with marginal notes relating to people in Boston, Massachusetts, and Lebanon, Connecticut, 18th century preachers, books, sermons, a meeting of the General Association of Connecticut, the Great Awakening, and the Trumbull and Williams families. Includes papers of Ellsworth Eliot (1864-1945), physician, of New York City, with material he collected in writing books; letters from Fitz Greene Halleck, S. F. B. Morse, Robert Sherman, and Eli Whitney; and legal documents relating to Nathan and Sarah Camp.
Eliot, Jacob, 1700-1766
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Ellsworth Eliot and William Inglis Morse in 1942.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains a wealth of information about the Eliot Family of Lebanon, Guilford, and New Haven, Connecticut. The members of the family trace their lineage back to John Eliot, "the Apostle to the Indians". The descendants of John Eliot refer to themselves as the "South End Eliots" to distinguish them from the "North End Eliots" associated with Harvard College and science in the nineteenth century. The chief figure in this collection is the Reverend Jacob Eliot, 1700-1766, Harvard College, class of 1720, and after 1730 the minister of the Third or Goshen Society of Lehanon, Connecticut. Eliot distinguished himself as an "Old Light" during the Great Awakening.
The second major figure in this collection is the second Doctor Ellsworth Eliot, 1864-1945, Yale College, class of 1884, who practiced medicine in New York City. Aside from his medical duties he was the author of The Patriotism of Joseph Reed, West Point in the Confederacy, and Yale in the Civil War. Part of this collection is material Dr. Eliot collected for these works.
Also represented are many brothers named Eliot during the nineteenth century, the sons of the Reverend Jacob Eliot II, 1734-1785, also of Lebanon, Connecticut.
There are also some letters from Roger Sherman, S.F.B. Morse, Eli Whitney, and Fitz Greene Halleck to various people, as well as a number of legal documents relating to Nathan and Sarah Camp, who probably were Dr. Ellsworth Eliot's parents-in-law and the parents of Walter Camp, the Yale football coach.
The first box in the collection contains the correspondence of the people mentioned above from 1700 to 1870. It is followed by various by legal papers relating to the estate of Jacob Eliot I his wife, and his son, 1734-1814. The legal papers relating to Nathan and Sarah Camp follow, filling the years, 1870-1885, and the last items in the box are papers collected by Dr. Ellsworth Eliot, including photographs of Jacob Eliot's Diary and congratulatory letters Dr. Eliot received from the people to whom he had sent complimentary copies of The Patriotism of Joseph Reed.
Also in box one is a scrap book kept by Whitney Elliott, 1823-1909, from 1875 to 1882. The book contains genalogical notes on the Eliot family especially in relation to the gathering in 1875 of the descendants of "Apostle" John Eliot at Guilford, Connecticut. The items are mainly newspaper clippings and poems.
Box 2 contains three bound books. The earliest two comprise the diary of the Reverend Jacob Eliot written in almanacs for the years 1716, 1721, 1723, 1724, 1726, 1737, 1741, 1742 and in the second volume 1745, 1746, 1747, 1749, 1752, 1754, 1757, and 1764. The daily entries are weather reports, but at the bottom of the pages and in the margins are notices of people in Boston and Lebanon, most every preacher of note in the eighteenth century, as well as information on books, sermons, and meetings of the General Association of Ministers in Connecticut. A great many notes refer to the Trumbull and Williams families. The most interesting entries concern the Great Awakening, the excesses of which Eliot strongly opposed. The most important entries have already been published in the Historical Magazine of America, 2d Series, volume V, 1891, pages 33-35.
Also in this second box is account book kept by Jacob Eliot I from 1754 to 1766 and continued by his son from 1768 to 1783. Besides financial matters the book contains notes of family marriages, lists of townspeople, and other minor items.
The third box contains a typed manuscript of Dr. Ellsworth Eliot's unpublished book on West Point graduates in the Union Army during the Civil War, a sequel to his West Point In the Confederacy, published by Yale in 1943.
Members of the Eliot Family Who Appear in this Collection:
Eliot, Abigail Ward, 1803-1838
Eliot, Alexander McGilvrae, 1802-1861
Eliot, Dr. Ellsworth. I, Yale 1849, Corn. Vanderbilt's doctor
Eliot, Dr. Ellsworth II, Yale 1884, 1864-1945
Eliot, Frederick Tyler, a brother of John H. Eliot
Eliot, Gustavus Rose, 1822-1869, a cousin of Alexander M. Eliot
Eliot, Henry, 1782-1864
Eliot, Jacob I, 1700-1766
Eliot, Jacob II, 1734-1785
Eliot, Jared Lay, 1805-1811
Eliot, John E., 1811-1880
Eliot, John Harvey, M.D., Yale 1805, 1784-1824
Eliot, Margaret, grand-daughter of Whitney Eliot
Eliot, Mary, mother of Fitz Greene and Maria Halleck
Eliot, Thomas, 1736-1809
Eliot, Timothy, 1772-1848,
Eliot, Whitney, 1823-1909
Eliot, William Horace, Jr., 1824-1852, Yale 1844
Eliot, Wyllys, 1779-1856
Other People of Note in the Eliot Family Collection:
Alexander, William, called Lord Stirling, 1726-1783
Banister, John, 1734-1788, member of Continentell Congress
Bartlett, Marietta M., amateur poet
Camp, Nathan S [underline] 1884
Camp, Sarah M. [underline] 1877
Clinton, George, 1739-1812, Governor of New York
Halleck, Fitz Greene, 1790-1867, poet and satirist
Halleck, Maria, sister of F.G.H.
Howe, William, 5th Viscount Howe, 1729-1814
Huntington, Samuel, 1731-1796
Morse, Samuel Finley, Breese, 1791-1872, painter and inventor
Pettit, Charles, 1736-1806, Revolutionary colonel
Reed, Joseph, 1741-1785, patriot
Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793, patriot
Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835, Revolutionary general
Wadsworth, Decius, 1768-1821
Whitney, Eli, 1765-1825, inventor
Williams, Alpheus Starkey, 1810-1878
Williams, Colonel William, 1731-1811, patriot
Trumbull, Jonathan, 1710-1785, patriot
This collection contains approximately 200 items in three boxes, including diaries, letters, and legal papers by and about Jacob Eliot, 1700-1766, of Lebanon, Connecticut, and his descendants, spanning the years 1916-1945 and including Revolutionary and Civil War material gathered by Dr. Ellsworth Eliot, 1864-1945.
The gift of Dr. Ellsworth Eliot and William Inglis Morse, 1942-1946.
Biographical / Historical
ELLSWORTH ELIOT, JR. B.A. 1884
Born June 6, 1864, in New York City. Died November 2, 1945, in New York City.
Father, Ellsworth Eliot (B.A. 1849, M.A. 1852; M.D. Columbia 1852), a physician in New York City; son of Wyllys and Lucy (Camp) Elliot of North Guilford, Conn.
Mother, Anna (Stone) Eliot; daughter of Joshua and Ruth Shaw (Sumner) Stone of Boston. Yale relatives include: Jared Eliot (B.A. 1706) (great-great-great-uncle); Harvey Elliot (B.A. 1805) (great-uncle).
Dr. Calliser's School, New York City. Dissertation appointment junior year; first dispute appointment Senior year; member Delta Kappa.
Attended College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University, 1884-1887 (M.D. 1887); on surgical staff New York Hospital 1887-1889; studied in Vienna and Berlin 1889-1890; surgeon in New York City 1890-1945; lecturer in clinical surgery College of Physicians and Surgeons and gave course called "Eliot's Quiz" to medical students 1890-1913; visiting surgeon Presbyterian, Gouveneur, Lawrence, Bronxville, and White Plains hospitals, and Northeastern Dispensary, New York City, 1896-1936; surgical director Knickerbocker Hospital 1930-1936; attended Medical Officers Training Camp, Fort Riley and Camp Crane, 1917-1918; commissioned Major April 7, 1917; went overseas August 15, 1918; surgical director Evacuation Hospital No. 11, American Expeditionary Forces, in Château-Thierry, St. Mihicl, and Argonne-Meuse campaigns; consulting surgeon Tours and Orleans section; returned to the United States January 23, and discharged January 25, 1919; author: Yale in the Civil War (1932), Letters and Palters of Ezra Stiles (1933), Theodore Winthrop (1938), West Point in the Confederacy (1941), and The Patriotism of Joseph Reed (1943); contributed many articles on surgery to medical journals; chairman surgical section New York Academy of Medicine 1909-1910; president New York Surgical Society 1909-1911 and American Surgical Association 1928; member Century Association, The Pilgrims, Grolier Club, and New York Genealogical and Biographical, and Historical societies.
Married June 15, 1904, in New York City, Lucy Carter, daughter of George Harrison and Lucy Carter (Wickham) Byrd. Children: Evelyn Byrd (B.A. Vassar 1928), the wife of Dexter Clarkson Hawkins (B.A. Harvard 1920; LL.B. Columbia 1922); and Lucy Carter (B.A. Vassar 1935).
Death due to lymphosarcoma. Buried in Alder Brook Cemetery, Guilford, Conn, Survived by wife, daughters, and there grandchildren.
Dr. Eliot presented to the University Library many books and other gifts, especially manuscripts of importance in the history of Yale and the United States. In 1927 he established in memory of his father the Ellsworth Eliot fund for research and publication.
Families; Great Awakening; Connecticut; Lebanon (Conn.: Town) -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Diaries; Clergy; Camp, Nathan S., d. 1884; Camp, Sarah M., d. 1877; Eliot, Ellsworth, 1864-1945; Eliot, Jacob, 1734-1785; Eliot, Whitney, 1823-1909; Halleck, Fitz-Greene, 1790-1867; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793; Whitney, Eli, 1765-1825; Trumbull family; Williams family; United States Military Academy
- Inventory, 1716-1947
  - Correspondence, 1729-1869 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1733-1814 (Box 1)
  - Camp family papers, 1848-1885 (Box 1)
  - Later Eliot family papers, 1885-1947 (Box 1)
  - Whitney Elliott: genealogical scrapbook, 1875-1885 (Box 1)
  - Jacob Eliot
    - Diaries, 1716-1764 (Box 2)
    - Account book, 1754-1885 (Box 2)
  - Ellsworth Eliot, Jr.: manuscript re: West Point in the Union Army, undated (Box 3)